Guide to the Shizuko Yamamoto Papers MSS.235
Fales Library and Special Collections
Shizuko Yamamoto Papers
1965-2010
Fales Library and Special Collections
Yamamoto, Shizuko, 1924-
Snyder, Kezia
MSS.235
33 Linear Feet in 26 record cartons, 7 card boxes, 2 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, and 1 flat file folder.
47 VHS
22 audiocassettes
2 CDs
2 DVDs
The collection consists of materials Shizuko Yamamoto created and gathered throughout her career as a shiatsu practitioner and macrobiotic specialist. Materials include research files, notebooks, conference and workshop packets, photographs, correspondence, recipes, clippings, books, magazines, pamphlets, patient files, audio and video recordings. The collection primarily consists of Yamamoto's books and research files pertaining to shiatsu, macrobiotics, yoga, and alternative, non-Western healing methods. The materials date from 1965 to 2010.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Kezia Snyder in 2009; an additional accession was donated in 2011. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2009.235 and 2011.235.
Conditions Governing Access
Series IV: Patient Files contain sensitive data, and researchers should contact fales.library@nyu.edu for more information. The remainder of the collection is open without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Biographical Note
Shizuko Yamamoto is a well-known shiatsu practitioner and macrobiotic consultant. In her native country of Japan, Yamamoto studied alternative and non-Western healing methods including shiatsu, seitai, yoga, and macrobiotics. After living in Tokyo for 40 years she moved to New York in order to share her knowledge of and promote macrobiotic and shiatsu practices. During her time in the United States, Yamamoto worked as a macrobiotic chef for Gloria Swanson and several macrobiotic restaurants. She provided shiatsu treatments in combination with macrobiotic diet recommendations and guidance to clients suffering from various ailments. Yamamoto is the founder of the International Macrobiotic Shiatsu Society, and served as president of the Macrobiotic Center of New York from 1970 to 1990. She also taught shiatsu and macrobiotic seminars across the United States and Europe. Yamamoto is the author of several books, including Barefoot Shiatsu,The Shiatsu Handbook, and Whole Health Shiatsu.
Arrangement
This collection has been organized into four series: Series I: Research Files; Series II: Books and Magazines; Series III: Correspondence and Photographs; Series IV: Patient Files.
The contents of each series have not been physically arranged by an archivist and the materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of materials Yamamoto created and gathered throughout her career as a shiatsu practitioner and macrobiotic specialist. The collection primarily consists of Yamamoto's research files, books, and magazines pertaining to shiatsu, macrobiotics, yoga, and alternative, non-Western healing methods. A small portion of the research files contain commercial and non-commercial audiocassette tapes, CDs, DVDs, and VHS tapes mostly relating to prominent figures in the macrobiotic and alternative medicine community. To a smaller extent the collection contains correspondence and photographs from friends, family, and clients. The collection also contains patient files documenting Yamamoto's consultations and treatments for patients with various ailments.
Collection materials include research files, notebooks, conference and workshop packets, photographs, correspondence, recipes, clippings, books, magazines, pamphlets, patient files, audio and video recordings. Some of the materials are in Japanese. The materials date from 1965 to 2010.
Macrobiotic diet.; Macrobiotic restaurants.; Acupressure; Alternative medicine.; Food Consultants.; Medical consultants.; Snyder, Kezia; Yamamoto, Shizuko, 1924-
- Series I: Research Files, 1965-2010; 13.9 Linear Feet in 12 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 card box, and 1 flat file folder.; 47 VHS; 22 audiocassettes; 2 CDs; 2 DVDs
  Arrangement
  The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor. Paper materials are listed first, followed by audio and video recordings, and two objects are listed at the end.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I: Research Files contains Yamamoto's research materials on shiatsu, macrobiotics, yoga, and alternative, non-Western healing methods. Research files consist of notebooks, conference and workshop packets, printed material, recipes, clippings, audio and video recordings. The audio and video recordings consist of commercial and non-commercial audiocassette tapes, CDs, DVDs, and VHS tapes. The content of most of the audiovisual materials pertains to prominent figures within the macrobiotic and alternative medicine community such as Michio Kushi, George and Lima Ohsawa, and Louise Hay. The content of several of the VHS tapes is unknown due to lack of labels. Some of the materials in Series I are in Japanese. Materials date from 1965 to 2010.
  - Research materials, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hawaii trip materials, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Japan trip materials, 1980-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - Master courses, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Research materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Research materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 14th Annual International Macrobiotic Conference, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Research materials, 1988-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3-7)
  - Macrobiotic Shiatsu Seminar Workbook, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - The Kushi Foundation - Dietary Recommendations and Recipes, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Research materials, 1999-2007 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - AIDS articles, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Research materials, 1986-2003 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Orando cooking and shiatsu classes, 1994-1999 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Research materials, 1976-1997 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Macrobiotic research materials, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Rice research materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Research materials, 1985-1993 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - The Natural Spa Seminar, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Macro Scope newsletters, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Research materials, 1966-1992 (Box 3, Folder 6-11)
  - New York City guidebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Research materials, 1985-2006 (Box 3, Folder 13-19)
  - Research materials, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Research articles and newspaper clippings, 1984-2004 (Box 4, Folder 5-8)
  - Macrobiotics Teachers Conference, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Research materials, 1990-2003 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Research materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 14-17)
  - American Organization for Bodywork Therapies of Asia - Membership Directory, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Macrobiotic Shiatsu Seminar Workbook, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Research materials, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 20-22)
  - Research materials, 1991-1997 (Box 5, Folder 2-5)
  - Research materials, 1994-1999 (Box 5, Folder 7-12)
  - Research materials, 1997-2006 (Box 5, Folder 14-22)
  - Research materials, 1991-2003 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Notebooks, 1982; undated (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
  - Research materials, 1990-2003 (Box 6, Folder 7-12)
  - Research materials and notebook, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Bahama trip materials, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
  - London trip materials, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Palm Springs and Napa Valley trip materials, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Roma, Parma, and Saltburg trip materials, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - China trip materials, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Research materials, 1977-2000 (Box 8, Folder 1-9)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Macrobiotic articles, 1984-1999 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Greece trip materials, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
  - Italy trip materials, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Research materials, 1986-2000 (Box 8, Folder 15-20)
  - Research materials, undated (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Business cards, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Kushi Foundation Physicians' Macrobiotic Studies Program research materials, 1987-1989 (Box 9, Folder 15-16)
  - American Shiatsu Association - Honorary Member Certificate, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - American Oriental Bodywork Therapy Association - Certified Instructor Certificate, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Research materials, 1990-1993 (Box 10, Folder 2-6)
  - Research materials, 1985-1993 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Kushi Foundation Summer Conference, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Kripalu Experience program materials, 1987-1988 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Rice research materials, 1980-1984 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Research materials, 1974-1992 (Box 10, Folder 13-17)
  - Research materials, 1975-1994 (Box 10, Folder 23-27)
  - Research materials, 1982-2007 (Box 11, Folder 1-15)
  - Michio Kushi articles, 1994-2002 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Research materials, 1985-1995 (Box 11, Folder 17-24)
  - Getting Whole Grains to 3 conference, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Yamamoto's workshop materials, 1985-2006 (Box 11, Folder 27-31)
  - American Organization for Bodywork Therapies of Asia - Certified Instructor Certificates, 2001-2005 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Research materials, undated (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Kushi Foundation articles, newsletters, and promotional material, 1979-2010 (Box 27, Folder 1-8)
  - Energie Kaarten posters, undated (Flat-file-folder 10 Right)
  - Acupuncture poster, undated (Flat-file-folder 10 Right)
  - Michio Kushi lecture on microbiotics and intuition, December 15, 1984; cuid41466 (Box 28, Audiocassette cuid41466)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Duration: 96 minutes; Preservation note: Side 2: first minute and fourteen seconds is a snippet from Beethoven's 6th symphony, then continuation of side 1 content continues.
  - Michio Kushi lecture and group activity on dietary balance and lifestyle, December 15, 1984; cuid41467 (Box 28, Audiocassette cuid41467)
    Duration: 96 minutes; Preservation note: Side 1: at 00:44:43 new, unrelated content begins and lasts until the end of the side.
  - Michio Kushi lecture on cooking styles and energy forces, December 16, 1984; cuid41465 (Box 28, Audiocassette cuid41465)
    Duration: 64 minutes
  - Interview with Lima Ohsawa - audio recording, 1987-04-14; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Lima Ohsawa, Trans. Herman Aihara, April 1987; cuid41468 (Box 28, Audiocassette cuid41468)
    Duration: 41 minutes; Preservation note: Side 1 has poor audio, side 2 is blank.
  - Community Health Foundation and Shizuko in London - audio recording, 1988-1989; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Dr. Anthony Sattilaro, Recalled by Life - audio recording, 1988-08-12; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Corrective exercises, SH2 - audio recording, 1986-07-08; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - George Ohsawa, Fundamental Principles of Yin and Yang - audio recording, 1965; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Self Healing: Creating Your Health, by Louise L. Hay - audio recording, 1986; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Laugh for the Health of It: Laughter Therapy for the Whole Family, Created by Lino and Jane Stanchich - audio recording, undated; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Junsei Yagi Shigin - audio recording, undated; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Macro Myths, Steve Gagne, 1 of 2 - audio recording, 1989-11-17; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Macro Myths, Steve Gagne, 2 of 2 - audio recording, 1989-11-17; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Wisdom of Aging Panel, Kushi Institute Summer Conference - audio recording, 1997; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Singing Lesson, 1 of 3 - audio recording, undated; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Singing Lesson, 2 of 3 - audio recording, undated; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Singing Lesson, 3 of 3 - audio recording, undated; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Voice Lesson - audio recording, undated; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Shizuko, Music - audio recording, undated; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - AIDS: A Positive Approach - audio recording, 1983; 2 audiocassettes (Box 13)
  - Laugh for the Health of It, Lina and Jane Stanchich - audio recording, 2002; 1 CD (Box 13)
  - Radio Sotokoto - audio recording, 2006-08; 1 CD (Box 13)
  - Barefoot Shiatsu - video recording, 1990; 2 VHS (Box 13)
  - Barefoot Shiatsu: Macrobiotic Shiatsu Workbook - video recording, 2004; 1 DVD (Box 13)
  - Michio Kushi's Life Story - video recording, undated; 1 DVD (Box 13)
  - Unlabelled video recordings, undated; 45 VHS (Box 13, Box 14)
  - The Macrobiotic Center of New York - corporate seal embosser, 1985 (Box 13)
  - Magnifying glass, undated (Box 13)
- Series II: Books and Magazines, 1968-2008; 13 Linear Feet in 12 record cartons and 1 flat box.
  The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
  Series II: Books and Magazines contains publications from Yamamoto's library pertaining to shiatsu, macrobiotic living and cooking, yoga, nutrition, acupuncture, and alternative non-Western healing methods. Some of the books are authored by Yamamoto herself, including Barefoot Shiatsu,The Shiatsu Handbook, and Whole Health Shiatsu. Other book authors prominently represented within the series include Edward Esko, Wendy Esko, Louise Hay, Alex Jack, Aveline Kushi, Michio Kushi, Patrick McCarty, George Ohsawa, and Lima Ohsawa. The most common magazine titles within the series are Amberwaves, AOBTA Pulse (American Organization for Bodywork Therapies of Asia), Christina Cooks, Compas, Healthways, Ignoramus, Macrobiotics Today, Macrobiotique, and Vegetarian Times. Some of the books and magazines are in Japanese. Materials date from 1968 to 2008.
  - Books, 1970-2006 (Box 15, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 21, Box 23, Box 25, Box 29)
  - Magazines, 1968-2008 (Box 16, Box 17, Box 20, Box 22, Box 24, Box 26)
- Series III: Correspondence and Photographs, 1965-2007; 11 Linear Feet in 11 record cartons.; The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
  Series III: Correspondence and Photographs contains Yamamoto's personal and professional correspondence with family, friends, and clients. The series also contains personal photographs with a small amount of professional photographs from workshops or events Yamamoto attended. Some of the correspondence is written in Japanese. Materials date from 1965 to 2007.
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hawaii correspondence and photographs, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Japan correspondence and photographs, 1980-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Correspondence, 1986-2007 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1998-2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1982-2004 (Box 2, Folder 18-21)
  - Photographs, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Shizuko Yamamoto birthday party guestbook, 1984-06-01 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1995-2004 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1980-2003 (Box 4, Folder 10-13)
  - Correspondence regarding donations for The Macrobiotic Center of New York, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Bahama photographs, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - London photographs, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Roma, Parma, and Saltburg correspondence and photographs, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1965-2001 (Box 7, Folder 1-26)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1984-2006 (Box 9, Folder 4-14)
  - Naropa Institute correspondence, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1990-2007 (Box 10, Folder 18-22)
  - Letters of recommendation for Yamamoto, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Postage stamp collection, undated (Box 12, Folder 2-14)
- Series IV: Patient Files, 1977-2002; 3.7 Linear Feet in 6 card boxes and 1 manuscript box.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Series IV. Patient Files contain sensitive data. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu for more information.
  Series IV: Patient Files contains the files Yamamoto created for patients she consulted and treated for various ailments. The files consist of index cards with patients' contact information and reason(s) for consultation. The materials contain sensitive data and researchers wishing to view these materials should contact fales.library@nyu.edu for more information. Materials date from 1977 to 2002.
  - Patient Files, 1977-2002 (Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36)